Hello, I'm your host, David Barnard, and
my guest today is Thomas Petit, an
independent consultant focused on
subscription app growth. Over the past
decade, Thomas has worked with hundreds
of clients and helped manage tens of
millions of dollars in ad spend. On the
podcast, I talk with Thomas about
setting sensible goals for paid
marketing, how to measure and learn from
the results, and why a single ad
creative can completely change the
trajectory of a company.
Hey, Thomas. Thanks so much for joining
me on the podcast today. It's a second
or third time on, but I'm super excited
to chat. We've a lot to talk about.
Yeah, thank you very much. I'm really
happy to come back. I'm a huge fan of
the other episodes, and I have to say
you have really a great diversity of
guests. So, I hope I can keep the bar
really high, but I'm really happy to
come back for a new topic today.
The reason I wanted to have you back on,
one, your past episodes were amazing,
but we talked about very timely things.
We talked very specifically about ATT,
and we didn't talk as much about general
principles around growth. But, the main
focus of what I want to get at today is
that I've been talking to so many
developers struggling with paid UA. The
funny thing is this is not a new thing,
right? Paid UA has always been hard, and
there's a little bit of romanticism of
like pre-ATT it was so easy, and that's
not true. But, it's just a thing that so
many apps struggle with. Any marketing
struggles with, like, how do I make the
unit economics work? And so, that's what
I wanted to kick off with today, since
you talk to so many developers like I
do, but then you actually work as a
consultant with a lot of them to like,
"Okay, how do we actually make it work?"
I don't have to work that side of the
equation personally, so I love talking
to somebody like you who is day in day
out with multiple apps. Your job is to
help them make it work. I wanted to kick
it off with your thoughts around kind of
the minimal viable status, minimal
viable app, minimal viable company,
whatever that context around when you
should start thinking about paid UA.
Like, what does it take to actually
start making it work?
Yeah, that's a tough question, but I
think it's good to ask the question, to
be honest, especially in the early
stage, like when you really go from zero
to one and you don't like have a bunch
of data behind about how it's going and
so on, like when you're starting. I see
too many people like just straight
jumping in and I want to spend this
money on Facebook or whatever without
having done a bit of a health check of
why I'm doing it, what I'm going to try
to achieve, what stack does it take. And
a lot of it comes around goals and you
have to dig in but why? But why? Again
and again. Cuz usually they just tell
you I want to accelerate. I want more
revenue. I want to accelerate. But why
can't you do it otherwise or why do you
think paid is the solution? And most
importantly, like what are you minimum
bar on this? Especially minimum bar of
return. Like, what are you expecting
from paid for every dollar you put out
there? Are you expecting to make three,
five, half of one? And all these
situation can justify themselves in
cases. When you have that clear, you're
going to avoid a lot of the bad
surprises. Sometimes it will lead to
dead end. I have one app I work with and
I've been working with them for quite a
while. I was chatting with them for
years before we started working
together. And they come very clear to
say, "If anything can't run at at least
two weeks return straight from the money
we put there, we're not running it.
Period." And I say, "Yeah, but given the
metrics you have, it's going to shut
down a lot of options and channels and
so on." I say, "Yeah, but this is what
we're willing to accept and anything
below that is trash." I say, "Okay, I
mean, that's how you take it." And on
the one channel I'm helping them with,
we do manage to reach that goal, but
only up to a certain scale and there's
no more than that.
Apple search ads, I imagine.
In this case, it's Apple search ads, but
like
It also happens elsewhere, particularly
on Android for subscriptions, like even
on other channels. I have the same
problem with Google Ads for another
client. It's good to set the bar, like
what are you trying to achieve? And in
some case, you start understanding how
aggressive people can go. Like in some
cases, accelerating fast is actually a
priority because there is a first mover
advantage or market share matters a lot
or there is a network effect or I work
with a developer who was putting money
on the table that they were not going to
recoup directly, but they needed a
critical mass of users for the app to
have enough value so that then it
started create that virtuous loop. And
they had their goal really clear, but I
think a lot of people who go from zero
to one, they're just like
Oh, I want to accelerate. That's it.
I want more revenue. I'm saying, "Wait,
but what are you expecting?" So, I think
that that's really one. And very often
it's about return goals, but in some
cases it's about achieving velocity and
network effects, critical mass or market
share. Or on your marketplace, it could
be I want to rebalance what I have. I
had one case of a marketplace where they
had a ton of seller for one category,
but no buyer. And they had a ton of
buyer for another category, but no
sellers. And so, we run acquisition
specifically aimed at rebalancing a
little bit these categories. Where on
surface, it looked like it was
expensive.
But eventually, it enabled the other
users not to leave to avoid loss,
basically. Basically, know your
expectations and know what you're after.
And I think a lot of people, they don't
ask this question in a deep enough way.
Yeah. Or they give too simplistic of an
answer. I think if you ask most people,
the answer would be, I want to spend a
dollar and get a dollar 20 back.
Within 30 days or whatever that answer
might be. And And that's the
expectations going into it. But I think
That's already very specific. That's
That's pretty good to know it at that
point. I I uh, I hear that, I'm like,
"Okay, at least these guys know what he
can afford and I consider the time frame
and he's looking at that." Like, there
are already a lot of sub question that
are answered in the way you frame it.
So, I would qualify this as a fairly
advanced way to define the goal.
I think it's an advanced way to define
the goal, but for most apps, it's a very
unrealistic way to define the goal. And
that's was the point I was going to get
at is that it's easy to say that, right?
It's easy to think, "Okay, my goal is to
get a return on ad spend." But when you
only have, let's say, a thousand people
who've ever downloaded your app, you're
very early. Like, it's just very
unrealistic with a thousand ever
downloads that you're going to start
doing paid UA. And this is what I hear
from people, like, "Oh, we're just going
to turn on marketing and like we're
going to make money." It's like, "No."
Like, the very first step
is that your first goal should probably
be to get to a certain floor of monthly
active users where you understand if you
even have product market fit. Like, with
a thousand people, you don't actually
know what your unit economics are. With
a thousand downloads, you don't actually
know if your onboarding is working. You
don't actually know if you're even in
the ballpark of what you should price
the app at. There's so much context
behind the goals that if you're really
early stage, the goal maybe is just we
know we're going to lose money, but
we're going to lose money doing paid UA
in the service of experimentation,
dialing product market fit,
understanding our audience, just getting
live warm bodies into the app and see
how it goes. Because if your goal is to
get a return on ad spend as an early
stage app, that's probably not going to
happen. And then I think there's other
contextual goals as well. If you're a
VC-backed company and you need a big
outcome in the long run, that's a very
different goal than if you're bootstrap.
Like, I was talking to a guy who has
amazing ASO, he wants to grow his
business, but he can do it in a more
methodical way. He's very profitable. He
built a model that I can spend on paid
UA if my return on that investment is
relatively confident at 366 days. So, he
takes all the initial conversions and
then discounts the renewals. You know,
he knows whatever 40% of my annuals are
going to renew at year one. So, if you
take the revenue on my 7-day free trial
conversion and you take 40% assumption
of when you renewal, as long as I'm
profitable at day 366,
I can cash flow a certain amount of paid
UA and then that 40% is going to renew
the next year at 60 or 70% and then the
next year after that. And so, he's going
to build this bigger business over the
long haul by having a goal that doesn't
sound amazing. It sounds scary to a lot
of folks on paper, but the context of
his app that can work. So, I think
you're right that anybody thinking about
paid UA needs to be more introspective
and realistic about what they are going
to be able to achieve with paid UA
versus just thinking I'm going to start
spending money and generating a profit
on this and getting a direct return on
ad spend.
In some case, you might want to start UA
very early and not even build a base
before. Maybe you know that's going to
be the channel and you want to know from
the very beginning where you are at. Or
you even want to iterate on the product
from this kind of traffic. And that
actually happened to me once. Almost
like the first app where I got the whole
budget for myself was really, okay, what
are the goals? And I like we need to
have at least 500 new users per day to
iterate on this onboarding, on this
paywall and get retention data that is
we're not going to achieve it
organically. We don't have the time to
build the organic. We're going to do it
in parallel, but we need to accelerate.
We can afford to lose that amount of
money, but we need this amount of users,
and we need to learn within 3 months how
much is coming back, and we basically
need to measure all of this to prepare
for what was coming next. I think here
it was clearly a VC-backed startup, but
they knew from the start that this is
how they would grow, and so for them it
did make sense to start early, but not
with a I'm going to return to X on that,
but rather to like let's build the app
towards that. Let's build the
foundation, and let's also learn in the
process not just to iterate on product,
but let's learn the earliest possible
what messaging is working. This is what
we're going to put in the store, what
kind of creative is working, because
we're going to build the team and all
the infrastructure to buy in terms of
also in metrics and tools. So, it was
really like learning goal, like bring
the user, but also within 3 months we
need to have all of this list checked,
because we want to accelerate, and this
is the goal in this case. So, there are
many kind of goals. I think there's
another check that really needs to be
done. I call it cash availability. It is
what can you really afford? Because
return is never guaranteed. Like
sometimes it's a bit of a roller
coaster, you don't really know. You open
a new channel, you scale up, you start
from zero. Even when you're stable, it
change. So, don't assume that you're
going to be at this goal. There might be
some loss, maybe there's a time of
learning period for the algorithm as
well, and so on. And so you need to
check a little bit what's the cash
availability. In the case of the example
you gave about the developer who could
afford to have like over a year of
payback on the renewal, he also knew
that he had enough cash in the bank to
finance this acquisition before the
money was coming back. So, that's
something that's quite important to
know. If I had to frame it in a bit of a
trivial way, I'd say only gamble money
you can afford to lose. Maybe it's going
to come back, but maybe not. And even if
it comes back, it may not come back in a
week. So, can you actually afford to
finance this? Or maybe you need to
change a bunch of things before you can
actually get there. So, cash
availability is important. I have
another case of somebody from Subclub
actually to whom I'm talking to where
they're fairly at this stage they've got
a bit of a base of organic, but the cash
availability they have for paid UA is is
fairly limited. It's in the very low
five digits total, not even per month.
And then raise the question of should
you actually do any of it? And some
channel can be operated at at low scale
to some extent.
Maybe Subclub, maybe influencer. But
most of the bigger platform that use
algorithmic optimization, so that's
valid for Meta, TikTok, Google, but
that's also valid for all DSP and
networks and so on, do not go there with
$20 a day. It's money lost. Like you're
not going to learn anything, but you
can't really make the machine work at
all, not going to pass threshold,
there's a bunch of like criteria. And
that minimum bar of the amount you can
put to actually start seeing something,
whether you like what you see or not is
another question, but to actually
and learn from it as reason over time.
10 years ago it was a lot more manual
and there was less events, and now it's
more and more, let's say, automated, and
that can work really well in some case,
but if you invest too little, it's
doomed to fail, even if your product is
fantastic.
With Facebook, I know so much of this is
automated with the happy path, you know,
where they want you to spend your money
is through the algorithmic ad buying.
But are there still ways on Facebook, so
if somebody does just have $20 a day to
spend, can you manually go in and if you
really know who your audience is,
actually set up more manual campaigns
and spend that $20 a day with like super
highly targeted, picking your audiences
and stuff, or is that just not even
possible anymore?
It's technically possible. I would
strongly recommend against it.
Okay.
There are many reasons. First is the
targeting, like people say, is never as
narrow precise as you think it is. So,
that's one. Even if you use advanced
things like lookalike 1%, like kind of a
very narrow audience, but the rest is
kind of even if you limit the
demographics and the interest and the
lookalike and maybe a specific area and
you reduce the So, there's a bunch of
problem that comes. First, when you do
that, Facebook tends to penalize you. If
the audience is not big enough, you may
not get any delivery at all. That's a
possibility. And that's most likely
you're going to get it extremely
expensive. Like if you want to go so
narrow focus, you're going to pay such a
premium to do that that it's probably
better to let Facebook figure it out on
itself and actually go for these users
at a cheaper price by itself. Like it's
probably more efficient. There is an
additional factor or two even.
One is if you're not optimizing like for
downstream events, it's most likely
you're going to be served garbage
because Facebook and other platform,
they are going to preserve the inventory
that is most likely to convert to those
who buy for this. Like when you're
saying to Facebook, "Oh, I'm trying to
get free trials." Let's say. What is
going to happen in the background is
their whole machinery is going to
calculate in real time that that
particular user who's done this on
Facebook, this on Instagram, also
interacted with this advertiser before
has converted on a bunch of other apps
and seeing that creative, what's the
likelihood of that impression converting
into actually this event?
And so, they preserve this high-value
inventory for whoever optimize for that.
If you run at very low scale, you
obviously can't optimize for event.
There's not even enough data. So, you're
going to start buying on install or on
clicks or even on impression. What
happened in this case is Facebook serves
you the inventory that is not going to
convert. And so, as you buy on CPI, the
install to trial is going to drop. If
you buy on click, people are not going
to install. There's a bunch of people
who actually don't install apps on
Facebook and Instagram. And obviously,
if I'm buying on install on trials,
Facebook is going to show my ads to less
of these people. But if you tell them
you have to click, they say, "Oh, I've
got a bunch of people who are likely to
click and do nothing else. So, that's
the one I'm going to give you." And so,
if you're a big brand and you go on full
CPM and you say, "Okay, my goal is to be
seen. I want this campaign to reach
eyeballs. I don't need them to take an
action." Facebook is going to do it, but
they're going to actually serve you
people who are never going to do
anything because they preserve the other
inventory. So, that's the second thing
is if you're not optimizing for
downstream event, it's likely that the
quality of traffic is going to be less.
And the third reason So, there's a
premium. You're going to be served to
people who don't convert. And the third
one, specific to iOS, but it's going to
be the same on Android at some point, is
that through the aggregation of data, so
I don't want to be too technical at this
point of the podcast, but basically with
aggregated data and the sampling of
whoever has consented, you're going to
be blind basically on who converts or
not. Facebook is not even able to
aggregate enough data to even report to
you how many install or conversion have
happened. So, you're going to hit, let's
say, minimum thresholds that Facebook is
going to be blind, you're going to be
blind at some point. Either it's going
to stop delivering completely or you're
going to cut it because they say, "Okay,
nothing is coming back." or something
like this.
There's multiple reasons not to operate
at very, very low scale, at least on
algorithmic platforms.
So, I know this is hard to pin down, but
we were talking about cash availability
as we were going down that rabbit hole,
which I think was a really good one to
go down so that people really
understand. I mean, I didn't understand
that. I thought maybe there was a chance
to like spend $100 a day and make it
work through manual targeting or
whatever. But what then is the kind of
minimally viable cash setup. I mean,
there's layers to this, right? That
people who already have a high average
revenue per user, they've got good
retention, they've got good conversion
to trial, conversion to paying, if all
of those things are really well dialed
in and the onboarding is really well
dialed in, you can start to get closer
to return on ad spend profitable
quicker, where maybe you don't need a
million dollars in the bank to do this
big experimentation. But, what would you
say are guardrails? Like, you really
need to have six figures in the bank
that you can and even six figures in the
bank you could lose before you try and
scale up on these algorithmic platforms?
Or, what are the general guardrails
around that?
I usually think about it more in terms
of volume of data to be able to optimize
than in volume of cash, but then you can
relatively convert one into another to
give a bit of a ballpark. To give a
simple answer, I think in my case, I do
try to aim at five digits monthly
budget. And, if you go per platform and
assuming you don't have too much
distribution of country and platform and
so on,
I'd say somewhere between 10-20 grand a
month, I wouldn't start anything below
that. Otherwise, it's doomed to fail.
There's also within this budget, who is
going to actually execute it? And, if
you don't have a person in the house,
maybe you can do it yourself and learn.
And, actually think that's the best in
the early stage. But, as soon as you
want somebody to manage it and if you
need to hire, you're not going to hire
somebody who cost you two, three, five
grand if your budget is 10 grand. If you
want to go with a freelancer, nobody's
going to accept you if the fee is not,
let's say, 1K a month or 3K a month or
whatever, depends the country as well
and you might change country. Or, if
it's an agency, they also have minimums.
So, I'd say you can operate on 10-20K,
but then it's only also one channel and
I think that's kind of a bit of a risk.
You might want to start with just one
and so on. But I'd say for me like the
area that I find really hard to nail is
the 0 to 50k because 50k months is where
you can start having two three channels
running in parallel, or even I can split
the budget between campaigns and start
making a bit more of experiments. And
let's say this kind of budget obviously
depends the vertical and a bunch of
things, but it's basically down to the
fact that this kind of amount, so let's
say 15k months is roughly $500 a day.
That might convert into a couple
hundreds install a day, or if I take the
example of the US, it actually is the
same the other way because the installs
are cheaper, but they convert lower. So,
let's say you you put $500 on the table,
and maybe you're going to get 1 200
installs, and those are going to do 10
or 20 trials. So, depends a lot. Maybe
your trial rate is higher, maybe you get
cheaper install because your creative is
awesome or whatever. But then you start
having these 10 20 events per day in the
campaign that I believe are a bit of a
minimum, otherwise it's going to really
struggle. If you're sending Facebook two
events a day, it's never going to learn
who your users are, the sampling is too
hard, and the fluctuation is going to be
extremely hard to read even for you. So,
that's how 10 20 events per campaign per
day backfills into that's going to be 10
or 20k months on this channel.
Makes sense.
And then ideally more.
That's the thing. There's also a ceiling
where you've got an efficiency of scale,
but on the other side, there's some
point that you want so much of it that
you go to broader audience, they convert
less, or Facebook start ah yeah, if you
want 100 install, maybe I'm going to
serve them at $2, but if you want 10,000
install, then you're going to have to
pay $4. Like, it's a bit caricatural,
they're not the numbers, but the logic
is there. And I think at the beginning,
if you're able to provide 50 events
instead of 10 every day, it's obvious
that the company is going to run better.
But at some point, I mean, this is not
going to an infinity number. There are
also ceilings that you start hitting.
I think a lot of the folks I was
referring to early in the podcast who
are really struggling to make it work,
for them, I think this is probably the
issue is that they're trying to make it
work on 5 to 10k a month.
That's really hard zone to operate in.
And if you take more than 5 years ago,
and I'm not talking even pre-ATT, we're
not saying UA was easy, but you could
operate at a lower scale. Basically,
because the platforms were a lot more
primitive and they didn't have this kind
of level of optimization and machine
learning and what not that they have
today. So, you could narrow it down to
I'm going to do this lookalike here and
I'm just going to bring the traffic and
it's going to convert. And because there
was not the tools that they have today,
but there was also no privacy threshold.
The zero to 50k a month is definitely
the harder part. I see more and more
people, agencies, independent that are
like, "Oh, no, I don't want these kind
of clients anymore." Because it's double
the work and half the reward. So, I'll
wait for them to have some kind of
validation. And then I am them scale.
It's more profitable for me. It's really
hard to go from zero to 50k a month,
that's what I believe. It doesn't mean
it's not possible. And one advice, maybe
if you've got 5 or 10k to test, probably
would be to avoid algorithmic platform.
So, search ads is I mean, the nature of
the inventory is very different, but the
mere fact that they're not optimizing
for anything after the install. And to
be honest, they're not even optimizing
for anything after the click.
Means that you can operate with a much
smaller budget. Influencers is also one
where you might want to try because you
can find influencer of the size that you
are and you can perfectly do a $100
operation or what not. And so, those are
my go-to channels, typically, where I
would start. I wish we had keywords on
Google that are only buyable. It's not
doable because the campaigns are
bundled. But back in the day when it was
possible, that was how I was starting.
Because one, it was operable at very low
scale. and two, at this stage you want
to learn what's working,
and search is a fantastic channel about
where is the intent, what is the
messaging that works. I see a lot of web
business that are putting budgets of 100
or 500 just to understand what makes
people tick. Return goal zero. I want to
know what is the message that is most
attractive to people. And this is
something that is quite harder to do now
because a lot of the platform basically
don't even let you do that. You could do
one just to get the creative on a
journey to your website or whatever, and
then bring this learning to the ads and
actually kickstart a bit faster. That's
something that I still do. Usually I do
it when the app is not even ready.
You're still in development or whatnot,
and it's a great exercise to do. Like,
what are the keywords that I search for,
and what is the messaging that actually
makes people tick.
At a small scale, do Google web search
ads, can you not still target to those?
Because people do go to the Google
search box, and you know, not Play
Store, but even iOS and Android, people
just go to the Google search box and say
best running app, best weight loss app,
or whatever. Can you not target those
directly in a Google search?
Yes, you can do that. On the web, Google
still allows to go like very narrow,
choose your keywords, run at very low
budgets, and so on. So, that's still
doable. They're kind of favoring whoever
optimize on conversion as well on the
web, but it's still a possibility, and
I've seen some campaigns work this way.
Usually the struggle at this point is
that a lot of developers, I mean, it's
really hard to maintain a good app and a
good website in parallel. You're going
to want to iterate on this landing page,
and so on. Is that you have to offer
some kind of user journey? You cannot
send to the store. Like, it's forbidden
by Google to use this campaign and have
them run straight to the store. So, you
have to have them go towards the landing
page. What I would recommend in this
case is actually to build something
really simple. Like take one of these
landing page builders like Unbounce or
Flow or Instapage or whatnot. Have the
market completely independent. Do not do
it on your own website because the
iteration is going to go slow. And maybe
you do something very simple. Simple
landing page that explains what you're
doing and redirects to the store. This
is possible on a very low scale. The
thing is if it was that easy to make the
unit economic work, everybody would be
doing that. There are a few apps,
especially in the subscription space,
that do manage to get that journey to
work at some scale,
but it's definitely not the easiest one
to do. And so if you're starting and
you're already going to one that you
know is kind of hard to crack, the thing
is that it's full of learning. So I
would still recommend it, but knowing
that the unit economic might not be the
worst there, but you might get a ton of
learning for your SO, for imagery, for
what people are searching. So I do think
that's still doable, but I would say
that's really in the earliest earliest
stage. So we mentioned what is your
goal. We mentioned cash availability.
The last I do, even if the cohort is
small, is what kind of revenue per user
are we getting right now? And in a few
cases, I've said, "There's no chance
we're going to make it work no matter
what, so let's not even try." And
usually that's because our pool is
really low. I don't know. If you're
making 20 cents per install in the
state, there is no UA manager on earth
that can attract traffic that is going
to be profitable. Like period. Like So
running a bit of a very simplistic, very
basic, what approximately is my revenue
per user? I'd be struggling to say from
there you go. It's also very specific by
country and platform. And the price of
install is not like fixed. It can be
extremely different by vertical. If your
creative is really good across
platforms, it's hard to pin a value, but
over the years you learn by vertical
more or less like, "Okay, if you're
making less than a dollar in the states
on a subscription app, it's not going to
work. For some categories of gaming, $1
per install is actually a fairly
reasonable amount and you might make it.
If you're talking about countries where
the inventory is fairly cheap, like big
publishing country on Android, like
Pakistan, Indonesia, Egypt, like massive
populations where the inventory is
relatively cheap, if you get $1 per
install on those segments, there's
probably a way to make it work. Like so,
it's very relative, but so those are the
three checks, like goals, cash, and
Apple revenue per install.
I want to add some caveats to the
revenue per install side of things. I
think one important thing to understand
too is what your funnel looks like
currently and why. So, you know, this is
something I've talked a lot about over
the years, but you know, my apps have
been featured quite a bit. And what I
notice when my app gets featured is that
the average revenue per user drops
through the floor. So, if you're looking
at an app whose like primary source of
installs is the Apple loves the app,
that's great. free installs, it doesn't
cost you anything, but your average
revenue per user is going to inherently
be lower because of that. And then on
the flip side, if you're looking at the
unit economics where the app has really
good ASO and it's like the top result
for a very specific keyword, and 90% of
their traffic is people searching that
very specific keyword, the average
revenue per user could be $5, and it
looks amazing, like, "Oh, we're going to
make Pay to Win work. This is perfect,
like $5 per install, like we can buy
installs cheaper." But then the problem
you run into there is that the intent on
a paid install is nowhere near the
intent on a search install. And so, I
think taking into account the source of
that average revenue per user is an
important factor as well, because I've
seen that happen, too, where people are
"Our funnel's amazing, our unit
economics are amazing, like everything
is lined up and we should be able to
make paid UA work, and then they go try
and it doesn't work. And why is it? And
you dig a little deeper, it's like,
well, all their numbers are flawed
because they're from a very specific
targeted audience who has super high
intent and they just can't achieve that
level of intent with paid UA.
I don't know, absolutely. I mean, I'm
seeing apps where organic is actually
much lower converting and our pool than
paid and I'm seeing app where it's the
other way around.
I'd say it's still good to check and
yeah, make a check on sources as well.
There is variance. It still gives an
idea, but it's definitely And that's why
I don't want to put a number. Like I
don't want you to ask me, "Okay, so what
is the minimum output to run UA?" Like
because I can't answer this question
simply put. Like it's impossible. It's
still good to check, but you have to
take into account the context of what is
this cohort. There's also a scale
question that sometimes you manage to
find like an extremely niche cohort of
users at the very beginning, but then as
you broaden the audience, the behavior
is completely different and that happens
at different stages, not just at the
beginning, but like there are points
where you start breaking like the core
of the audience that is highly
converting and maybe the audience is not
big enough or so. There's a bunch of
caveats, but let's say those are the
checks.
We've talked through these kind of like
minimal viable situation. You need to
really understand your goal and then be
realistic about your goal.
You need to have a solid understanding
of your average revenue per user and why
and whether it's realistic to get that
with paid campaigns.
And then you got to have money. You got
to have the cash to spend it, but once
you do all that, you also then need
tooling to figure out what's going to
work. So,
you know, if you start with App Store
search ads, you don't necessarily need
any tooling, but what are the kind of
stages that you coach people through of
what you need to actually understand the
results as you do any scaling of paid
UA.
It's fundamental that you have a way of
seeing what's going to happen. No, you
put the money out and you want to see
something, like some kind of
measurement. So you're going to have to
have this in place. In some case, I can
see from the very beginning because of
the ambition or where it's going or the
kind of budget or whatever that this app
is going to go on multiple channel at
the same time and it's going to scale.
In this case, I'd say probably not a bad
idea to have an MMP, a mobile
measurement partner because if you have
it from the start, then your data is
unified rather than try both of things
and at some point 6 months later say,
"Oh, now we need it." And then really
hard to reconcile the data. So in some
case, I start straight on, but it's
actually not a requirement. If you're
starting just with influencer, basically
need almost nothing. I'd rather have one
of these magic link systems that the
MMPs are giving, but that you can
figure out as well otherwise. But
basically, there's no particular
measurement that is going to change the
result. If you're starting with search
ads and I mentioned these two channels
earlier in the podcast that I'd probably
start there when I have little money.
The framework for measurement for Apple
is entirely different from every other
network and it's free. There is a
self-attributing API that you can
install yourself. The MMPs are putting
it out of the box and there are number
of tools that enable you to also have it
without doing any kind of installation.
RevenueCat is one of those. It comes
outside of the box with what you're
buying. You can also do it yourself.
Like the API is open, you read the
documentation, you implement it. It's
not particularly complex. So here we
come to it depends the channel, see? And
here the tooling you need first brings
you to the question of actually where
I'm going to advertise, which brings the
question of who's my audience, who are
they? And thinking a bit of the kind of
user that is most likely to be audience
fit right,
you probably thought a little bit about
the user persona or have already data or
whatnot or I've just these preconceived
ideas that may or may not be true, but
you know that, oh, this is going to go
more on paid social and it's a younger
audience and I'm going to go for them on
Snap or on TikTok or whatnot or oh, this
is a very I mean, there's all kind of
people on Facebook, so everybody ends up
on Facebook. When I say Facebook, that's
Meta, so Facebook and Instagram, but you
might have an idea where this is going
and so you can see what is possible to
do. In the case of Facebook, you can
have the measurement. So, just to be is
through their SDK, which you can also do
it this way. There is a custom way
without the SDK that I would not
recommend. It's a bit clunky, but
basically when you go to Facebook, they
tell you, "Okay, do you have the
Facebook SDK? Do you have an MMP or do
you want to do it yourself?" And those
are the three methods. A lot of times
after search ads and influencer, Meta is
going to be the one where a lot of
subscription apps are going to start, so
that's why I'm mentioning that one. You
do not necessarily need the MMP. If you
start on Google, for example, because
your audience is in a country that is
heavily geared toward Android, in this
case, like market share of Android user
acquisition is massively on Google Ads,
like to a point that is really
impressive. Depends a lot where, but
let's say 50 to 70%. So, this is the
channel that is like kind of the obvious
way. Plus, it encompass search and
display and the Play Store, you can have
video and text, so it kind of makes a
lot of sense to go there. Let's say if
you're an app that operates in India
only, for me it's a no-brainer that I'm
going to start on Google Ads. And on
Google Ads, all you need is to have
actually Google system in place and
that's actually the recommended setup to
have Firebase. It's free to implement
and this is the best way to operate on
Google Ads. So, that's where I would
start. So, for me the question of the
tool really lays down on, okay, which
channel I'm going to start and where I'm
going in the midterm. At some point I
usually tend to want the MMP early on.
One reason is one to not lose any time
with custom integration every time I'm
going to have to open a new channel
because they have it out of the box, but
also because they're going to add on top
like this magic links and a bunch of
custom integration with ad networks that
you can't do any other way. Like a bunch
of networks they don't take you if you
don't have an MMP like period. When
Pinterest was doing app installs they're
not doing it anymore it was like this.
I'm not 100% sure but I do believe
TikTok is still like this. They said
that they would open something but I
don't know if they did because all of my
clients operate through an MMP these
days. At some point it's most likely
that you're going to want an MMP but it
is not needed for the start. If you're
going to only operate on Google, Apple,
influencer you can do without. Even
Facebook you can do without. So
especially MMPs are not free so you
might want to consider cost saving or
just testing because maybe you want to
validate that paid is a channel that is
going to work for you. And then you can
do it like kind of with a minimum stack
that is basically you have to install
the measurement that depends on which
platform you want to advertise. It's not
the same for every one of them so that's
why that's where you're going to go. I
would recommend to also look at Okay,
this is what the platform is going to
report the results but where am I going
to double check that what they say is
actually what's happening?
And typically what I do is infer the
incrementality or the difference from my
baseline. One from the consoles. So I
assume you have the App Store Connect
and the Play Console. They are free and
I don't think you can upload an app if
you don't have them anyway. So there's
an analytic path that you can access.
It's not particularly complex to read.
It's not particularly good either but it
gives you a data point. And the other
one is internal analytics. So some kind
of product analytics tool that might be
a more evolved one like Amplitude or
Mixpanel or that might be Firebase
because it's more cost-affordable or
that might be one of the dozens of other
alternatives that I didn't give the name
today. But having those product
analytics helps you really understand,
okay, this is the self-reported results
that the platform say, what am I
actually seeing on my side? Because
you've got all kind of case where the
network might over-report or actually
under-report. But there's not a lot you
need to have in place because I would
say you have the console and you should
have some kind of product analytics in
place even if you're not doing any kind
of paid UA. But it's important that
you're checking them in parallel.
So, we've been talking about how to use
tooling to actually measure the results,
to look at the Play Console, to look at
Apple's Console, to look at an MMP. But
I think what a lot of people struggle
with is what do you actually look for?
And on that subject, I'm going to
pre-prompt, give you some answers, but
then I want kind of your your feedback
on these answers. So, I just did a talk
in Vegas. I'll put a link to it in the
show notes, but I spent a lot of time
talking about blended subscriber
acquisition costs. And, you know,
essentially your blended customer
acquisition cost since we mostly talk
about subscription apps on this podcast
and that's what my talk was about, I use
subscription. So, you should be looking
at your customer acquisition cost and
you should be trying to figure out your
exact ROAS on the paid spend, but you're
not really going to figure that out
anyway. But the goal more broadly is to
acquire subscribers profitably.
And you're going to be doing that
through SEO, through ASO, through
influencers, through PR, through Apple
featuring you. Like there's so many ways
that your app is going to get attention,
and then some of those are actually
benefited by the paid UA. So, as you
spend a little bit, you're getting more
reviews, which helps with your ASO,
which helps with your word of mouth. And
so, ideally, like there's multiple kind
of flywheels in here.
And so, looking at a really high-level
at blended subscriber acquisition cost,
I think aligns incentives so that you're
not only focused on your paid UA, but
you're still pushing on SEO, you're
still pushing on ASO, you're still
looking for those organic channels,
you're still incentivizing word of
mouth. So, you're doing all of those
things. But, you do need to be in the
MMP dashboard figuring out, okay, am I
like just totally losing my shirt on
this paid acquisition? So, tell me about
how you measure the results and how you
look at both these high-level metrics
like blended subscriber acquisition
cost, but then also still try and get
some sense of what your return is on
that paid spend.
That's a super valid point, and more
than what my blended cost per paid
subscriber or whatever is, what is the
trend of this branded going as I pay
more or less? Because if you just take
the value and let's say you've got a ton
of organic and you start spending not a
significant amount, the blended cost per
subscriber still's going to look great,
even though your paid UA is doing
absolutely horrendous. So, it's more
about how it's evolving as I move spend.
And that's a must-have exercise to do.
One, because that's what's going to show
up in the P&L of the company. And two,
because that's the only thing you can
trust. Attribution is not exact science.
Like assigning where the traffic is
coming from is actually not something
that is going to ever be precise. And it
wasn't ever. And I think this is
something that is kind of interesting
that before ATT, about 2 years ago, most
marketers tend to trust whatever result
was coming indirect and take it for
granted. I always like, no, let's look
at the blended on top in parallel and
one to make sure that we're reaching
company goals overall and not just from
paid because if I succeed on paid, but
we're not making it in total, it's not
going anywhere. But two also because as
the time go, this conversion that are
getting reported are being more and more
modeled and sampled. And that creates
room for errors, especially when it's
the same company that is selling you the
ads that is responsible for the
modeling. So, it's a really healthy I
think the blended was always something
that had to be looking at. But it's
mostly the trend. I think the cost per
blended cost per subscriber is a great
one, but actually look at a bunch of
blended metrics and how many installs
moving, how many trials moving, how many
because you start detecting as well
like, oh, here I've bring a lot of
installs and a lot of trials from this
campaign. I can see how when my spend's
going up, these metrics are going up,
but the pace of paying subscriber is
not. And I already know that these
trials are the worst conversion than the
rest of the traffic, which is something
that most of the time the network cannot
inform you about because they use proxy
event and because they don't know have
the full development of the cohort and
so on. So, I get a real hint of is this
actually profitable?
And is this nature of traffic really
different? And sometimes it looks in the
network that I'm achieving my goal and
I've got a ton of your manager who told
me to bring these trials at $20 per
trial and I did it. I was like, yeah,
but your trials are the worst, like
they're killing me. I said, yeah, but
that's the only metric we have in there,
so what can I do? I was like, you look
at the blended, you look like me. So,
it's a really healthy thing to do. The
thing is looking at the blending,
there's a lot of things you infer. There
might be a lot of noise, seasonality,
featuring, other product change that
happened in parallel that makes the
picture gets a little bit more blurry
and that's how it is. And it's still to
still look into it. We still use the
metrics that are given by the ad
networks themselves or the MMP or
whatnot because looking at the total
doesn't enable you to optimize the
campaign at all. You don't get the
creative level, you don't get the ad
group level, and you have to
directionally trust what you're seeing
being reported directly to actually make
the change. Very often what I do is kind
of I make my budget decision and budget
allocation based on what I see in the
blended, but I'm going to make deep
channel specific change based on what
the network is reporting. And that's
really the normal exercise of any
marketer to be juggling between both of,
"Okay, what do we do strategically? What
do we do tactically?" All the time.
That's how the game is played these
days. It should have always been played
this way, but that's how we eventually
got there.
So, what I hear you saying and the
takeaway is that
you should be looking at whatever tools
you have at your disposal, whether it's
an MMP, whether it's the Apple Search
Ads console, whether it's Facebook's
console, Google's console, or whatever
combination of all of those you have
access to, you need to be looking at
those to get a sense for cost per
install, cost per event, some estimation
of return on ad spend, and make as much
inference and optimization you can that
level, but then you're always looking at
the higher end level of blended
subscriber acquisition cost, but then
also looking at blended funnel
analytics, like looking at all of your
primary metrics, and then essentially
doing incrementality testing. I made
this big change adding a channel, how
are those users interacting with my
onboarding? How are those users
converting to paid? How are those users
and you look at all those different key
metrics to make some inference on
whether that campaign is actually
performing at the level that maybe the
MMP or Google Play console or whatever
is telling you they're performing at,
you need to like trust but verify. And
the way you do that is looking at the
trends that as you make changes,
what changes are you seeing in your
results? So,
do you specifically
make big changes like dramatically to be
able to see that? Like will you ramp up
spend for a few days and then ramp it
back down to like do these
incrementality tests? And then are there
any good tools yet for doing this and
modeling that kind of incrementality
across product and subscription life
cycle events and everything else?
That's kind of my bread and butter
personally. Like one because I like it
and two because most marketers either
don't like to do it, don't know how to
do it, or don't want to do it, or
whatever reason. Usually they're the bad
ones. Higher the other ones that do it
all the time.
But you have to do it because
attribution is never an exact science.
The only truth is the blending. I'll add
something and it adds complexity, but it
actually un-blurs the picture a lot is
that there are very very little
interaction between countries and even
between platform. So, I usually run
these analysis on a country plus
platform segment. So, I will only look
at Brazil Android and I look at the
trends at the spend, at the install,
etc. etc. And I'll look at the US iOS.
Sometimes I would bundle them into
groups so that it got more volume
because if I'm looking at Costa Rica
alone, maybe it's three installs a day
and I'm seeing nothing. So, I'm going to
bundle all of Central America or
sometimes I don't bundle them
regionally, sometimes I bundle them by
level of similar conversion or whatever.
So, you have to do it in a segmented
way. But, this kind of a must-have
because that's the only truth. That's
the only way you're going to infer
anything.
I personally do a lot of it manually,
but that's also because I like it.
That's something that was not so common
until a few years back. So, the tooling
around it, they're fairly new. And the
platforms, like the networks are
Facebook and Google specifically, have
open-source models to do media mix
modeling and try to infer. The one from
Facebook is called Robin open-source and
you can build on top. The one from
Google is called lightweight. So, you
can have a team of data analysts
actually build on top something that is
specific for you. There are also tools
that are out of the box. I've used one
for over a year that's called
Incremental from Mao. Really nice guy.
Perfect timing. He was preparing this
and then suddenly ATT comes like a
visionary.
A lot of founders are a bit visionary,
but I think he had really a good sense
of timing. So, good for him to be there
before this happened. There's a couple
of tools that appear in that space.
Recast is one that was not specifically
made for apps and that preexisted.
There's another one that's called
metric.works. Their founders are
publishing very interesting stuff
regularly. So, I follow what they say.
Those tools, I'd say, if I'm operating
at a certain scale, I probably want one
of them. If you're small, it's not just
to justify the cost, but there's just
not enough data for these tools to
operate properly.
And the thing is you can do it in a
quick and dirty way pivoting an Excel
spreadsheet or having a Google Studio or
like Looker Studio or whatever for very
minimal cost and level of reliability
that's still interesting. It enables you
to filter and clean because you've
ramped up your spend only in one
country, so you're going to zoom in
there and you just pivot the data
quickly. And very often you need to
clean up a bit because there was
interferences from elsewhere that you
want to clean. Yeah, I'm going going
that day because there was the featuring
and I'm going to remove January because
what not in my space. There's a lot of
cleaning in this data, so
actually doing it manually is very often
not a bad idea. And if you're operating
at a small scale, for me it's obvious
that Excel is enough. You can you use
Google spreadsheet if you want.
Yeah, the other thing too is that I'm
hearing parallels from pre-algorithmic
Facebook and Google is that five or six
years ago part of what worked about
manually managing all these campaigns
and targeting and look-alikes is that
actually gave you a lot of insight into
your users and like who was your best
potential customer and how do we go find
people like that? And now for a lot of
the big apps that is outsourced to the
models and you have to use other means
to understand those customers and then
you're not able to like target them more
directly. And so I think part of what I
hear you saying too is that you say you
like it. Yeah, I used quotey fingers
there for people not watching the
videos.
Thomas says he likes it. I would assume
part of why you like it is not just that
you're a nerd and like to nerd out on
all this stuff, but it's that it gives
you a really deep understanding of
what's actually happening. Is it when
you spend the extra $5,000 this week on
influencers on TikTok you know if those
influencers and whether their TikTok
audience is actually working for your
opportunity not and then that informs
future decision-making. You understand
you made a big change in creatives and
you realize, oh wow, like that creative
did not land. Sure, it drove clicks, but
that's not the goal. So it sounds like
you actually learn a lot by doing this
kind of analysis as well that then
informs the rest of product decisions of
future marketing efforts and everything
else.
Absolutely. I mean there's a bit of
both. I'm a bit of a nerd, but there's
also a lot of learnings that I had that
I had to get otherwise, and they're very
complimentary. Like, it doesn't replace
making user interview and so on. It
comes on top. Like, it's kind of another
vision.
It's true that the networks, partly
because it wasn't their interest, but
partly for privacy reason as well,
provide a lot less detailed granularity
on the audience where we're showing up.
But, actually there's a lot that you can
infer also from the creative themselves.
Like, because you see how people react
on the video, and it's still first-party
and so on. And this is fascinating to
see how people actually act with
different message outside of your
product. So, also extremely
complimentary. One thing about the
nerdiness about it, like I've always
checking funnel revolution and segments
all the time for like every day for
weeks, months across many segments
is at some point you develop some kind
of instinct about the pulse of the
product that is going. And as soon as
something happens, and it can be that
it's a campaign that is going sideways.
It can be that it's a product change
that has completely unplanned
consequences. Or it can be a change in
seniority, but you see it instantly. And
very often it's kind of I can act on it
also as well. Or, oh, last year I
concluded that this was seasonality. I
need to prepare this year ahead. And
when you're doing it all the time, I
believe it gives you a unfair advantage
or fair advantage in this case just
because your level of knowledge is
better of I'm going to anticipate. I'm
going to make the better decision. And
I'm going to detect stuff that happens
earlier instead of let them run for a
while and suddenly, oh, what has this
going on here for weeks where we're
losing money on that particular segment,
but it wasn't showing up overall because
it was too small to move the overall
needle, but we're still losing money
there. And I love getting to that point
where you've done it so often that it
become really instinctive, and you stop
feeling it like, oh, I can sense that
something is happening there, so I'm
going to I had a bunch of discussion
sometimes like either we start a list or
PMs or whatever say, "How did you
thought about getting there? Why did you
split iPads there? Or why did you look
at Latin America that day?" I was like,
"One, I'm looking at those all the time
and you're not and you should. So,
that's the first answer. And second is
if you do it all the time, you start
getting a sense for it." And it's a very
exciting point. One, because I'm a nerd,
but actually from a business sense of
view because it basically enables us to
improve results faster.
So, we've talked about a lot of aspects
of what it takes to make paid UA work,
but we kind of glossed over so far one
of the most important things. Is you
actually have to like make ads and you
actually have to make I was I was going
to say good ads. I will revise my
phrasing and say you have to make
performant ads. Sometimes the most
performant ads are actually the worst
looking ads, which is such a funny quirk
to me. Yeah, let's talk creatives. Like
can you outsource this? Is Midjourney
creatives going to be a thing? What's
that kind of minimal viable creative
department to actually think you're
going to be able to be successful at
ramping up paid UA?
We had to talk about it because I mean
there's such a massive part of paid UA
success. I remember the early days of it
wasn't that important. I mean the
pressure on that was less. People were
less used to ads and honestly we were
putting like random stuff that was
working. It was fantastic. I would put
the same ads that I was putting eight
years ago. I would go in straight to the
wall like it's clear. The importance of
ads has grown a lot in particular
because a lot of other levers have been
removed like as everybody gets more and
more automated in a bunch of ways. And
most of the network these days just
okay, tell me how much money you can
afford and what is your goal. The only
thing you have left is what you input as
a creative or creative assets. So, this
is your lever. This is how the battle is
won or lost. And I think we should all
pretty much have it put in the minimum
requirements in the sense of what
message do you want to put? And it goes
deep inside two things, which is
understanding your audience and what
triggers them in this,
what you have different, what is your
USP, and so on. Which for me is
something you have to think before you
spend the first dollar.
And then it goes on an iterative mode on
what works and keep iterating on it. One
thing that is a bit maddening
and makes it very not scientific is that
not that it's random, but it's
unpredictable. I used to have a saying,
which is ugly wins, but the truth is you
cannot anticipate what's going to win.
If you show me 10 ads and you ask me
which one is going to be the most
efficient, the likelihood of me finding
the ads is at best the same as randomly
picking, okay, let's say that one. And I
realized also for me it was actually an
advantage that I saw a lot of people
thinking like, oh, I know this one is
going to work better because of this and
this and
Because I knew from the beginning that I
was really bad at anticipating which ads
was there. I had zero like criteria
about I'm going to show them all and
made a winner win, no problem. I think
here the creatives like they have to
anticipate, but they're also really hard
to interpret why it's winning, which is
even more surprising.
But the thing is when a creative starts
to win, luckily for us, so it's
complicated to design and prep, it's
complicated to analyze in terms of why
it's been working, but it's not
complicated to see what is working.
Because the platform they're incredibly
good at showing the creative that works
better. Insanely good at with just 100
or 200 impression I put 20 ads and they
already detected that this one is going
to get and it's getting most of the
spend. Like that's basically the signal.
Like the creative winner is the one
that's getting all the spend. And 99% of
the time the platform was right. They do
have a couple of false positive and
false negative, but that's the
exception. So here, in terms of how do
you deal with that, one is understanding
your USP and your audience, one is
really understanding the platform, like
because kind of the format that can work
for a Tik Tok is completely different
that what works in the store and search
ad and completely different that what
works on Pinterest and on Instagram and
on Maybe you can recycle a Tik Tok on
Reels, but YouTube is going to be
another beast. What is the context of
this? Oh, people are playing that kind
of game. I could put this. And here
comes the problem that a lot of
designers and app producers do not
necessarily have the context of where
the ad is going to be placed and at
which point the user is going to see it.
And that creates a lot of losing ads
because this has not been factored in,
even though it's still hard to plan, but
at least like taking a bit of context.
Then it takes a lot of testing. I mean,
finding a winner is really tough. The
thing is when you find a real winner and
testing them cost money,
but when you find a real winner, it's
game-changing. I mean, but like really
game-changing. I can't remember a couple
time in history where we find like a
It's not a 10x winner, it's a 100x
winner. It can change the course of the
company to find one. Like it's vastly
understated how you could completely
change the course of a company just by
finding this winner. But for this, it
means you deploy and it's a bit of a
number game of you have to test a lot of
things. One of the most common mistake
in creative is people are testing 20
variants of the same concept. Like
they're testing over and over the same
thing with small variants. You have to
test radically different thing. Is it a
person or is it an animation? Is it
provocative or is it really bland? Is it
strong color? Is there a lot of text?
Like there's so many elements that you
can change that is not even the message
you're communicating with the format.
Like let's take a longer video, a
shorter video. Do we start with the app
or do we start with a person or do we
start with whatever? And you have to be
really radical. For me, the framework is
really we're going to test a lot of
different concepts even if they're not
completely finished and polished and
nice. Wherever we get a bit of traction,
this is where we're going to add layers
of let's do violence of this. Like there
is a bit of traction there. Let's dig.
Let's drill down. And okay, let's test
in another order. Let's test longer.
Let's test with another person doing the
exact same. Let's take the same scene or
let's change elements after elements
until we polish this winner.
And one thing you said is at the
synthesis ugly wins that sometimes like
the ads that are most performant they're
not the ones that you would want for
your brand to communicate. Maybe they're
even completely off brand guidelines. I
had a ton of problems with other teams
say, this is what you're showing to
users? Like this is detrimental to
company in the long term. Like this is
problematic. I say, yeah, but it's
bringing twice as much the money. So
no-brainer. I'm going to keep showing
it. He's actually finding ways of okay,
here I've got a winner. How can I
realign it a little bit with
I know this concept is winning, but also
it might have consequences in the long
term that I'm not seeing because UA is
very short-termist. So not only try to
find variants and the elements that
work, but actually also realign it with
the message that the company wants to
give. That's really a complex topic. I
personally predicted two or three years
ago that we would start seeing the role
of creative manager, I call it. There's
not really any naming for it. And I'm
surprised to see that it's not more
standardized because the need for this
is massive. Everybody is doing it, but
it's completely unstructured. And you
ask also a little bit about
externalizing and so on. Personally,
when I get this question, I'm like, I
want both. I want to have a designer
in-house. I want to call creators. I
want to use agency to produce ads. And I
want you to try that. Like shoot a video
selfie on your own and let's Let's it
works. I know a bunch of companies where
the best performing ad is actually the
CEO shooting himself like in a very poor
environment, like old phone, whatever,
it's blurry, whatnot. That often works.
And the idea behind using different ways
of production is that everybody's going
to come with extremely different
concepts and styles and so on. And
that's the only way to find winners. If
you always rely on the same person to
create ads, no matter how good is this
person, you're going to hit a ceiling
because we're all limited in our
creativity range, let's say. So, I
basically want different people to do
this. And this is why over the course of
the last 2-3 years, not just because
influencer marketing was growing, that
advertiser used creators more and more
not to reach their audience, but to
actually use their ability to understand
the channel to produce content. When we
talk about user-generated content, like
UGC, the ads that are created by
influencers, mostly, it's actually
creator content. Because they know the
rule of the platform, they're really
good at making these videos that don't
look like ads as well, so people are
going to skip less. And on paid social
at least, it may not be true for every
channel, but it's clear that content
created by creators is what has been
winning in the last 1 or 2 years. That's
what the younger generation wants to
see. And it's not the only way to do
ads, but if you're not doing any of it,
you're missing out on something huge.
That is fascinating. I haven't heard
anyone quite go as deep into the reasons
and the variety of things that need to
be taken into account. I think there's
so many people in the industry still
thinking we need to figure this out
in-house. Like our designer needs to be
the one making the ads. And it's
fascinating to understand why you should
not try and build intuition because if
you think you're building intuition,
you're handicapping yourself because
you're going to not do as broad of
experimentation. You're going to say
that ad's not going to work, and then it
would. The biggest takeaway for me is
just like don't rely on intuition. Don't
try and make ads you think are going to
work. Try and make ads that are ads.
There's another argument I think this is
interesting here to add a little bit of
a closure on creative. But there's
another element which is really the
creative is the targeting. Like most
platform you don't target people at all.
Like on Facebook you can, but the most
efficient strategy is just go broad. You
just put the country and I want people
to be at least 18, all of the US, and
have an iPhone. And then the creative
and the events that you're inputting are
doing the targeting work. And if you
only have one team, whether it's in a
house or even an external, they're going
to gear towards one concept that is
maybe attractive, and you might find one
winner this way or a couple. But you
want also the diversity in concept
because ads are going to work for
different audience, and you want them at
the same time in the account because
Facebook is oh, that ads resonate to
that kind of user, and that ads resonate
to that kind of user, and you can group
them differently, and actually expand
your audience, and find performance in
more groups that you would have find
otherwise. If you always keep milking
the same winner over and over again,
you're also missing out on a ton of
potential audience for your app. And so
you have to go broad no matter how niche
you are, there are always a ton of
triggers to different people, and those
they're not demographic criteria or
interest. They're really what you're
saying about your app, and how you're
saying it in the format. So that's also
why you want to never give all the
creative to one person. I don't care
whether it's in a house, even the
creators, you want to test a lot of
creators. Because if all your creators
are done by one creator, you run into
the same problem again. Yeah.
Yeah.
So, the one thing you did mention that
is a bit of intuition and maybe
something that should have some level of
focus in the I creative is the unique
selling prop. How do you incorporate
that into this variety of testing? Like,
in your mind, does an ad need to
explicitly say something about the app
bringing value? Does it need to say
something specific? But, then each app
has like multiple layers of unique
selling propositions, right? Like, my
weather app, I always think about this.
Like, some people just like to talk
about the weather. Some people care
about whether they need a an umbrella to
work today cuz they're walking. Some
people It's like there's so many
different kind of features that would
resonate with different audiences. So,
it's not that you pick one unique
selling prop, one unique feature, and
like all your creatives are just
variations on that. But, how do you
think about it? Like, ultimately, you're
still selling something. Is there some
like overarching principle that you
think about that an ad needs to, at a
minimum, communicate something?
The simple answer is no. Like, there's
no clear pattern of this kind of USB is
definitely most likely to work or like
this kind of expressing the USB.
There are some verticals where I insist
on this because you have to
differentiate in markets that are more
competitive. And so, it depends the
phase you're in, but one typical example
would be meditation apps where you could
go 5 years ago with a completely bland
message about, "Oh, we're doing
meditation." It might have worked. But,
a lot of people have tested them, and a
lot of products have grown, and now I'm
seeing founders come to me say, "Yeah,
I'd like to launch this meditation app.
Can you help me grow it?" I say, "Okay,
what's the twist? Are you a meditation
app for seniors? Are you a meditation
app for kids? Are you a meditation app
that is inspired by whatever philosophy
behind? Or, what's your angle? What are
you doing different from the others?" I
say, "Oh, no, I just have great content
around meditation. They said So you just
have the exact same stuff that the other
500 meditation apps that have been
running at billion dollars for the last
5 years? And I said yes.
Okay, we can't work together. So I think
in those vertical that extremely
competitive, you have to differentiate
with something.
But it doesn't mean that your twist is
what's going to work in the ads. Not
necessarily. Sometimes the USP come
after, sometimes the creative is just a
teasing that is not expressing what
makes you different. You're not saying
it there, you're going to say it later
in the app store or even in the product.
Maybe you can find success with a
creative for your weather app
that is just showing a funny situation
with umbrella of people losing their
umbrella and then the transition is well
done and people discover later that your
app is better for weather because of
XYZ. Like it doesn't mean that the USP
needs to be in the creative. But I think
you need to know your USP to test after
what users, see what makes them react.
Like it leads you to their interest and
very often the best ads there are bit
indirect. They're not about oh my app is
doing this, you want to download it?
Never works. But say okay,
people were interested in that, they
very often talk about the rain.
Find funny stuff about the rain, put it
on TikTok. Find hot facts about the rain
and put them on Reddit or Twitter. Find,
you know, oh that's what they're
interested about. This is going to be my
hook. The hook is like kind of the first
second or three seconds of your ad. It
is extremely important
because if people don't stop in their
scrolling, you're dead already. You need
them to stop on your ads. This is
fundamental. And very often if you talk
about what you're doing, there's no way
people are going to stop on your ad. So
you need to find kind of a hook and then
slowly transition and maybe it's not
even in the creative, transition into
what you're doing actually to solve that
problem or to do it differently. And
it's kind of tricky because sometimes
what the user want to see is not what
you're doing, and finding this way of
transitioning is not easy at all. So, I
don't think the USP needs to be in the
creative, and I don't think there is a
pattern, and I don't think there is a
particular recipe. I've seen creative
that are so different work for different
people. It's amazing to watch. Like, I'm
friends with the developer of Motivation
app, and developers call Monkey Taps,
very successful apps.
And its best performing ads of all time,
there were a screenshot of a
notification. And I've tried this trick
with other apps from not the same exact
USP, but let's say approaching USP,
never managed to make it work. Like,
sometimes it's the time. Maybe you had
something like really different in
there, or maybe it was the first, or
maybe what. And obviously you could see
in the notification it's an app, but it
wasn't particularly saying or how the
app was better or different, and that ad
just worked. Like, sometimes it's
surprising to see what works, but it's
also amazing to see that different
things work for different apps. So, have
to try a lot, like literally. It's hard
to do any other way than trial and
error.
Is there an example you can think of
where there wasn't even, you know, like
you're saying, for my weather app I
should try a TikTok ad that's just
people talking about the rain or rain
facts or whatever. If that's an ad, how
do you even incent people to then go
download the app? Are there examples of
like you just don't even need to incent
them to download the app? Or you did
talk about like transitioning from rain
facts to some mention of the app, but
how does that actually play out? Cuz it
just you're blowing my mind right now.
About just running ads that are so
indirect to the value prop of the app.
How do you span that gap from this hook
that gets their attention in the first
15 seconds to then they do still have to
go download the app?
Yeah, fair enough.
How does that work?
Sounds like you already owe me money all
the input and now you want the twist to
the secret sauce on top of it. Like
you're asking for a lot.
Now you're getting to the hard part.
It's the same. Like there's hardly a
recipe. I've seen ads that are
completely indirect and actually not
transitioning to anything. But just
because the ads are cool, people are
clicking on it or they're just curious.
I don't like to do that because one it
may not work, but also very often
because it crashed my Insta rate hard.
This something that is particularly
tricky is you need to be a bit fun or
provocative or even click-baity or
extremely indirect to actually interest
people on their feeds. But then
eventually you need them to download the
app as well. And this kind of relation
and transition is really the hard part.
Finding something funny to stop them in
the feed is
and you can clickbait all you want, but
if you clickbait too hard when they're
going to reach the app store, they'll
say, "No way I'm installing this app. I
was just here for funny cats videos."
And that's kind of a bit the secret.
I've seen some ads that work without
much of a transition just because the ad
was so good. But you can think of ways
of inserting your product somewhere in
the video. In some cases even just the
video is there and the end card. So if
people look until the end and there
would be something that presented. I
would try to think of something a little
bit more subtle in transitioning into
it, but it could just work of adding an
end card at the end. Like just say, "Ah,
we have a ton of this in the app." Even
though it was just a funny video or you
made a remake that's in the rain or
whatever. And then you transition
somehow. Like but
you can be a bit abrupt in the
transition because it's also part of the
joke. I think some of the best ads
they're actually in how they manage to
find this
funny moment or fun fact into where
actually bringing to this. Sometimes a
bit more obvious than others. I don't
know. For example, some of the most
successful Blinkist ads they're about
showing famous CEO or whatever.
This CEO is reading 500 books a day, and
that's already so close to the value
prop of what Blinkist is doing that they
can transition very easily, and it's
fairly natural. But, they find a way for
people to be interested like, "Oh, yeah,
I want to be as smart and successful as
that guy." And suddenly, "Oh, that's the
solution. Super cool. Like, that looks
simple as hell." And with the rain, I'm
sure you can find one. I'm more of a
nerd than of a data guy, so I'm not
particularly good on the content
creation and on these ideas that really
works, so I lean on other people to find
it. So, there's not one recipe. I would
recommend to transition somehow, but it
doesn't have to be transitioning into
this is what we do. Like, the USP, the
exact USP. Just to transition into we're
doing something around this problem that
you're going to like. You can tease a
little bit. I would recommend telling
people that this is an app. Otherwise,
when they get to the App Store, the
rejection is hard. Like, they weren't
expecting to go to the App Store, or
they're not even making the Okay, this
video was cool, and then move on. So, I
would recommend to find some kind of
transition, but you can try the brutal
method. Might work, but I would
definitely try to find a a slight
transition and tease a little bit
towards. Depends a lot on what you're
doing here. So, that's hard to
generalize as well.
You mentioned briefly in passing that
reducing your install rate is
potentially a negative thing. Are you
talking about that if you're running a
very clickbaity ad on Facebook, and your
install rate goes to crap, they're going
to show it less because you're too
clickbaity, and they have to show a
million impressions for you to get one
trial start, and you're optimizing for
trial starts, and so that super
clickbaity ad is just not delivering
enough to train the algorithm, and for
them to actually be able to deliver you
the impressions. Is that what you're
kind of getting at?
More or less. There are two things that
can happen that are both bad in this
case, or that you need to know as a
background. The first one is that maybe
the ad is very successful because you've
pushed it really hard. It can be because
you're click-baity and faking it, or it
could be because you really find
something super funny. And then the
engagement on the ad is going to be
insane. People watch it till the end.
They react, they comment, they like,
they share, they do whatever. Like all
the signals who create this are high.
Like people stop, they talk about it.
Like all those signals that give the
platform, "Oh, people want to engage
with this ad. I'm going to show more of
it." And then you get more and more of
these impressions, which eventually
you're going to pay one way or another
because no matter what the billing is
made on, and you're told that you're
paying for a trial or an install or
whatever, you end up paying for install
no matter what. It's just a conversion.
But then these impressions do not
convert into your action. You're not
going to get the raw as you want from
this, even if the traction is insane on
the creative. Because at the end of the
day, as the second thing is, the whole
logic of these auctions is
that Facebook or TikTok or whoever Okay,
you want trials? What I want, besides
user engagement, is to monetize
attention. And on this segment, the
benchmark is going to be $10 per
thousand install, like revenue per
install or revenue per million install,
we say in this case, but
I say, "Okay, so if the ratio to which
you convert an impression into an
install and a trial is better, then
basically for the same money you're
paying, the platform gets more money."
So they're obviously going to prioritize
you over every other advertiser out
there. And they're even going to charge
you less for every install and for every
trial, and they're still winning on
revenue on their side. If everybody
clicks on your ad, but nobody installs,
eventually your ratio is really bad,
which means that the money you're
willing to pay is little, which means
the platform is not making money, and
they're going to punish you for it at
some point. Like early on, they move
this creative a lot, you get traction on
the creative because it's engaging, but
eventually the unit economics doesn't
work for the platform itself. Like it's
kind of you want your goal, but one way
or another, Tik Tok, Google, everybody,
they're going to monetize the audience
at the rate that I mean, it's also a
balancing system. No, if everybody
starts paying less, Facebook is going to
accept that and they can not monetize as
well. It's not that they fix the price
of okay, that impression is $10. Like
it's a moving dynamics.
But you're in competition with like
millions of advertisers. If your ratio
of converting an impression into a click
into an install into a trial is lower
than your neighbor, you're either going
to pay more for it or you're not going
to get any of it.
All right, Thomas. So, this was supposed
to be like 45 minutes. It's going to be
about an hour and 15, hour and 20 minute
episode and we're not even halfway
through what we wanted to talk about
today. So, I've been threatening you
that we should be doing quarterly
podcast because it's just so insightful
and we get so much great feedback on
your episodes. So, if you're listening
to podcast and you want more Thomas
episodes, shoot me an email, hit us up
on Twitter. There's so much more we
could dive into, but we do need to wrap
up. I think the biggest question people
are going to be asking at the end of
this episode is how do I hire Thomas?
And unfortunately, I have to tell
everybody who asked me that question,
you can't hire Thomas. He's too busy.
He's almost never accepting a new
client, but I did hear recently you're
working with a group of fellow growth
marketers. So, you might have some
friends who have availability even if
you don't, but you do take new clients
here and there depending on
circumstances. So, if somebody wants to
get in touch, what's the best direction
to send them to work with Thomas or
somebody like Thomas to figure all this
kind of stuff out?
Yes, thanks David for the nice words.
You can try to email me or LinkedIn me,
but actually I'm pretty bloated over
there, so I would not recommend it. I'm
really easily joinable on direct
messaging Twitter. I'm in a bunch of
Slack. I'm in the Sub Club forum. And I
do try to answer to the best of my
ability. To add work is complicated,
although I do add some regularly. The
reason is what we were talking before
about the insight we make on the long
term. They require that you work in the
long term with people. I can't get them
in the first week. Like I've digged into
the data regularly and I also enjoy
seeing the development of the ads on the
long term. But I do know a bunch of
people that work on similar things.
Yeah, so ping me up. I try to answer
everybody. Email is just not the best
way. Yeah, it was really fun. You
mentioned maybe quarterly or maybe
another part. I'm going to tease a
little bit. The topic I did want to talk
today but I'm too talkative so we didn't
get is the balance between freemium and
premium and how hard you get with your
paywall. So hopefully in a few months we
have the chance to talk about that.
That's one of the topic that is keeping
me busy lately. So if you reach that far
in the podcast and you are interested in
that, do ping David so that we do
prioritize it.
Yeah, I know. I I was actually really
excited to talk about that as well. We
just did an episode with a current
Headspace PM and a former Headspace PM.
It was fascinating to hear Headspace's
transition from being a very freemium
product to being an almost completely
paywalled product. And there's so many
apps and so many examples of people
experimenting heavily with freemium and
premium right now. And so it's going to
be a fascinating topic. So I think we
just committed ourselves to doing this
maybe in September or October. So
Thomas, always a pleasure chatting and
look forward to talking more in the
future.
Likewise. Always happy to be back. We
still did a good one and we've got more
topics coming.
Thanks so much for listening.
If you have a minute, please leave a
review in your favorite podcast player.
You can also stop by chat.subclub.com
to join our private community.